Guide to the Lesley Blanch Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lesley Blanch papers
1850-2011
OSB MSS 202
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.5
(20 boxes)
The Lesley Blanch Papers contain correspondence, photographs, artwork, and printed material by Lesley Blanch or pertaining her life and work. Also included are personal and business papers related to her writings and estate, as well as a small amount of audio and born digital material.
Blanch, Lesley
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 17 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 18 (born digital): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bookblast LTD., on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2016.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. Correspondence, circa 1950s-2009. II. Photographs, 1907-2013. III. Personal Papers, 1960-2008. IV. Business Papers, 1945-2009. V. Printed Material, 1850-2008. VI. Audiocassettes, circa 1944-1998. VII. Electronic Media, circa 2001-2011.
Lesley Blanch
Lesley Blanch (1904-2007) was an English writer, historian, artist, and traveller. Her works and journeys focused on Russia and the Middle East. She began her career as an artist, studying painting at the Slade School of Fine Art at University College London. She later became a journalist, serving as the features editor of British Vogue from 1937 to 1944. Her first book, The Wilder Shores of Love, was published in 1954. Over the course of her life, she wrote 12 books, and a posthumous collection of her memoirs was released in 2015. She was married to Robert Alan Wimberley Bicknell from 1930 to 1941, and to French novelist Romain Gary from 1945 to 1962.
Scope and Contents
The Lesley Blanch Papers contain correspondence, photographs, artwork, and printed material by Lesley Blanch or pertaining her life and work. Also included are personal and business papers related to her writings and estate, as well as a small amount of audio and born digital material.
Authors, British -- 20th Century -- Archives; Journalists -- Great Britain; Artists -- Great Britain -- Archives; Women travelers -- Great Britain
- Correspondence, circa 1950s-2009; Series I; 1.25
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Notable correspondents include Joan Bailey, Romain Gary, and Susan Train. General correspondence is placed at the end of the series.
  Related Materials
  For additional correspondence, see photographs, personal papers, and business papers.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence and related materials such as photographs and drawings.
  - Aitken, Lex, 1992-2005 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, Joan, 1970s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bemelmans, Ludwig, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Beny, Roloff, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Blanch, Lesley, 1966 (Box 1)
    Contains an autographed card from Lesley Blanch to George Cukor.
  - Blanch, Martha, 1955 (Box 1)
    Contains a postcard from Martha Blanch.
  - Gary, Romain, 1967-2003; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Train, Susan, 1968-2004; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence about the fire, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Unsorted correspondence, postcards, related papers, circa 1957-2013; 14 folders (Box 3)
    Contain letters from Edna Fleming, Gerald de Gaury, Nancy Mitford, Julian Barnes, Pat Kavanagh, and Gore Vidal.
  - Postcards, circa 1960-1989; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Photographs, 1907-2013; Series II; 2.33
  Contains primarily photographs with some correspondence and other related papers. A small number of items in this series have fire damage. This is due to a fire that destroyed Lesley Blanch's home in France in 1994.
  - Photograph and invitation, Duke and Duchess of Windsor, circa 1960 (Box 4)
  - Photographs of friends and lovers, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Lesley Blanch and Romain Gary, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Roquebrune and mentor, undated; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Photograph album of Blanch's house, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Blanch and ancestors, 1907-1938 (Box 5)
  - Photographs of Lesley Blanch, various locations, circa 1944-2004; 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Photographs of Lesley Blanch and Romain Gary, Hollywood, circa 1959 (Box 5)
  - Large photographs, undated (Box 20)
- Personal papers, 1960-2008; Series III; 3.25
  Contains objects and papers related to Lesley Blanch's personal affairs, including those of her estate.
  - Address books, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Datebooks, 1977-2007; 14 folders (Box 6)
    Annual datebooks for 1977, 1990, 1995-1997, and 1999-2007.
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 7)
  - Christmas cards illustrated by Lesley Blanch, 1950s (Box 7)
  - Documents from estate, undated (Box 7)
  - French legal documents, 1960s-1990s (Box 7)
  - Orange handbag, circa 1970s (Box 7)
  - Souvenir register, undated (Box 7)
  - Awards, 2001, 2004 (Box 19)
    Includes the documents for the medal of Officier de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres (awarded to Blanch in 2004) and the documents appointing Blanch an Ordinary of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (2001), signed by Queen Elizabeth II.
- Business papers, 1945-2009; Series IV; 1.92
  Contains material related to Lesley Blanch's career as a writer, including clippings of articles she wrote, reviews of her books, and papers related to The Sabres of Paradise (1960). Also included are documents and other papers related to an unauthorized biography of Lesley Blanch (Boston, Anne. Lesley Blanch: Inner Landscapes, Wilder Shores. London: John Murray, 2014.)
  - Articles, circa 1960s-2006; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Articles on cinema, 1945 (Box 8)
  - Book reviews, France, 1977-2003; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Book reviews, 1954-2012 (Box 8)
  - Photocopy of article by Blanch, The Seven Veils of Islam, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 9)
  - Gertrude Bell piece, related papers, 1998- (Box 9)
  - Materials related to New College Library donation, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Materials related to posthumous memoirs, 2015 (Box 9)
  - Papers related to unauthorized biography, 1995-2009 (Box 9)
  - Theater designs, 1934-2006; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - CDs with material related to theater design, undated; 4 (Box 18)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Legal papers, 1966-2006; 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Eastern Eye, the Selected Writings of Lesley Blanch, undated (Box 11)
  - Research materials related to Sabres of Paradise, circa 1958-1968; 6 folders (Box 11)
- Printed material, 1850-2008; Series V; 6
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Contains articles, notes, and publications collected by Lesley Blanch, with some material from her estate.
  A small number of items in this series have fire damage. This is due to a fire that destroyed Lesley Blanch's home in France in 1994.
  - Articles, 1850-1999 (Box 12)
  - Book jackets, undated (Box 12)
  - Exhibition booklets, 1975-2002 (Box 12)
  - Papers about Iran, 1976-1978 (Box 12)
  - Postcards, blank, undated; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Travel papers, 1970s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Christie's Monaco: Collection de M. Henri Clarke, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Magazines, 2006-2015; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Royal Society of Literature Review, 2008 (Box 13)
  - Clippings, 1954-2007; 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Notes and clippings on friends, 1978-1998 (Box 14)
  - Obituaries and related papers, 1996-2007; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Articles and photocopies of articles, undated (Box 19)
  - Vogue articles and related materials, undated (Box 19)
  - Interviews and related papers, 1970s, 2000s; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Books, 1890-2004
    - Poètes russes du XIXe siècle, 1936-1954 (Box 15)
    - Annotated copy of Romain Gary: Le Caméléon, 2004 (Box 15)
    - Prayer book from Violet Trefusius, undated (Box 15)
    - Annotated copy of Three Sisters and Other Plays by Chekov, undated (Box 15)
    - Une Sultane Martiniquaise a Constantinople, 1937 (Box 15)
    - The Costume of the Theatre, 1931 (Box 15)
    - Two books about Russian monastaries, 1958 (Box 15)
    - The George Cukor Collection catalogue, 1986 (Box 15)
    - Vers Ispahan by Pierre Loti, 1925 (Box 15)
      Handbound volume.
    - Notes de Route by Isabelle Eberhardt, undated (Box 15)
    - Pages Choisies by Pierre Loti, undated (Box 15)
    - Pages D'Islam by Isabelle Eberhardt, 1932 (Box 15)
    - Looking Back by Shusha Guppy, 1991 (Box 15)
      Autographed copy.
    - Annotated copy of Constantinople by Pierre Loti, 1890 (Box 15)
    - Unbound books
      - Bakst: The Story of Bakst's Life, undated (Box 16)
      - Oriental carpets, undated (Box 16)
      - Pictures for the Tsar, undated; 2 folders (Box 16)
        Labelled "from Pictures for the Tsar" on original carrier. Possibly a partial copy of Photographs for the Tsar by Sergei Mikhailovich Prokudin-Gorskii.
      - Tschechonin, undated (Box 16)
      - Unbound book in Russian, circa 1900 (Box 16)
- Audiocassettes, circa 1994-1998; Series VI; 1
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Materials within this series maintain the original organization found at time of acquisition.
  Contains audiocassettes with contents by or related to Lesley Blanch, including recordings of several memorial broadcasts aired after her death.
  - Interval reading: Journey into the Mind's Eye, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Journey into M.E., BBC Reading, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Journey into the Mind's Eye: Passions - Proq 4 of 5 - Journey, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Romain Gary breakdown, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Romain Gary l'insaisi, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Romain Gary: Une vie, une oeuvre, undated; 1 (Box 17)
    Note on tape label reads "Bad Quality."
  - Roquebrune (Mangham, Mitford, Press & Vale), undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Sara Davies, Juliet Stevenson, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Stimme der Hoffnung, 1994-08-29; 1 (Box 17)
  - Stimme der Hoffnung, 1996-04-01; 1 (Box 17)
  - Stimme der Hoffnung, 1996-05-05; 1 (Box 17)
  - Stimme der Hoffnung, 1996-05-11; 1 (Box 17)
  - Stimme der Hoffnung, 1996-05-13; 1 (Box 17)
  - Stimme der Hoffnung, 1996-03-25; 1 (Box 17)
  - Teresa Cherfas interviews Lesley Blanch, undated; 1 (Box 17)
  - Writers' France: Writers on Paris 1920 on / The Riviera; Lesley B. on Train Bleu and Maughan, 1997-12-26; 1998-01-02; 1 (Box 17)
- Electronic media, circa 2001-2011; Series VII; 0.25
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Contains born-digital material created by Lesley Blanch and recordings of memorial broadcasts aired after her death.
  - Autobiography, floppy disk, 2001-06; 1 (Box 18)
  - "Last Word: Lesley Blanch," CD recording of BBC Radio 4, 2007-05-11; 1 (Box 18)
  - Memorial CD, undated; 1 (Box 18)
  - New Yorker cartoon clips, CD, 2011; 1 (Box 18)
  - "Une vie, une oeuvre: Lesley Blanch (1904-2007)," CD recording of France Culture, 2008-05-22; 1 (Box 18)